{"tossups": [{"question": "This composer composed a suite for viola and strings on the death of King George V, and his requiem for Franklin Roosevelt is based on a Walt Whitman elegy for Lincoln. This composer of<em> Trauermusik</em> and<em> When Liliacs Last In The Dooryard Bloom\u2019d</em> included the \u201cTurandot\u201d scherzo in his<em> Symphonic</em> <em>Metamorphoses of Themes by Carl Maria von Weber</em>, and Nazis censored his opera about the painter of the Isenheim Altarpiece. For ten points, name this German composer of<em> Mathis der Maler</em>.", "answer": "Paul<b> Hindemith</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One politician in this family drew ire when he ordered his police superintendent, James Conlisk, to use lethal force against protesters rioting after MLK\u2019s assassination. A woman who married into this political family was nicknamed \u201cSis.\u201d The aforementioned man with this surname was accused of fabricating votes to hand the state of Illinois to Kennedy in the 1960 election, and his son was succeeded after six terms by Rahm Emanuel in 2011. For ten points, identify the surname of Richard J and Richard M, two mayors of Chicago.", "answer": "<b> Daley</b> family (accept Richard J and/or Eleanor and/or Richard M<b> Daley</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This group, which was responsible for the Dos Palmas kidnappings in 2001, split off from the similar MNLF after being funded by Osama bin Laden. In 2016, this group abducted Indonesian sailors off the Sulu Archipelago. For ten points, name this ISIS-allied terrorist group that operates in the southern Philippines.", "answer": "<b> Abu Sayyaf</b> (or<b> ASG</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler was restored by a military force known as the Hundred Thousand Sons of St. Louis, which put down Rafael del Riego\u2019s uprising and ended the \u201cLiberal Triennium\u201d period. The Cortes of Cadiz was disbanded by this ruler, whose tyrannic last ten years of rule were nicknamed the \u201cOminous Decade.\u201dSupporters of this ruler\u2019s brother, Don Carlos, opposed this ruler\u2019s rejection of the agnatic succession clause of Salic Law when he designated Isabella II as his successor in 1833. For ten points, name this king of Spain, whose death led to a succession crisis that sparked the Carlist Wars.", "answer": "<b> Ferdinand VII</b> (or<b> Fernando VII</b>; prompt on Ferdinand)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Sara, a person with this surname, invented a recipe for baby formula while working with infants in Hell\u2019s Kitchen and twice traced epidemics to Typhoid Mary. A woman with this surname was the only female speaker during the 1963 March on Washington and was the first African-American dancer to get a lead operatic roles in Europe. A man with this last name served as White House Chief of Staff under Ronald Reagan and as Secretary of State under George H.W. Bush. For ten points, identify this surname of performer Josephine and politician James.", "answer": "<b> Baker</b> (accept Sara Josephine<b> Baker</b>; accept Josephine<b> Baker</b>; accept James<b> Baker</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Streetcars serve this city\u2019s First Hill and South Lake Union neighborhoods, and its industrial districts are concentrated along the Duwamish River. A 1971 billboard asked the last person leaving this city to\u201cturn out the lights\u201d after the US canceled a program to develop supersonic planes. An observation tower was built for the 1962 World\u2019s Fair here, and it is home to the Pike Place Market. Boeing was founded in, for ten points, what city on Puget Sound that is home to the Space Needle?", "answer": "<b> Seattle</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This group was stopped from raiding the Hansa Stavanger after the intervention of American security advisor James Jones. In one operation, Somali troops lit a large diversionary fire so that this group could neutralize \u201cCaptain Martyr Mahmud.\u201d After the Palestinian Popular Front hijacked a Boeing 737 to negotiate for the release of Red Army Faction leaders, this group successfully liberated Lufthansa Flight 181. This organization was formed after traditional police units failed to prevent the 1972 Munich massacre. For ten points, name this elite German counter-terrorism unit.", "answer": "<b> GSG 9</b> (or<b> Grenzschutzgruppe 9</b> der Bundespolizei; accept<b> Border Protection Group 9</b> of the Federal Police and similar translations)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s ideas were challenged by Nikolai Vavilov, who was then thrown in prison and died. This man claimed that by exposing plants to high moisture and low temperatures, he could convert winter wheat to spring wheat, a process known as \u201cvernalization\u201d or \u201cJarovization.\u201d This advocate of acquired characteristics was dismissed from the Institute of Genetics in 1965 after criticisms from his colleague Andrei Sakharov. For ten points, name this Stalin-supported pseudo-scientist, an anti-Mendelian thinker whose crackpot ideas on genetics influenced Soviet agricultural policy.", "answer": "Trofim<b> Lysenko</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "It was the first city taken by ISIS during its 2014 invasion of Iraq. For ten points, name this city near Baghdad.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Fallujah</b> (accept First Battle of<b> Fallujah</b>; accept Second Battle of<b> Fallujah</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The constitutionality of this action was argued<em> for</em> in Byron White\u2019s dissent in<em> Roberts v. Louisiana</em> and argued<em> against</em> by Thurgood Marshall\u2019s one sentence concurrence in<em> Woodson v. North Carolina</em>. In 1972, this action\u2019s constitutionality was initially rejected in a one-paragraph opinion, with all five majority justices writing separate concurring explanations. Four years later, the Supreme Court reversed its position on this action\u2019s constitutionality, establishing an \u201celigibility, then selection\u201d scheme that states are required to meet in order for this action to be legal under the 8th Amendment. For ten points, name this action that is, somewhat ironically, not considered \u201ccruel and unusual punishment\u201d since the ruling in 1976\u2019s<em> Gregg v. Georgia</em>.", "answer": "<b> death penalty</b> (or<b> capital punishment</b>; accept equivalents related to<b> execution</b>s, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "When an author was asked about terrorist attacks during this conflict, he responded \u201cbetween justice and my mother, I choose my mother.\u201d Frantz Fanon\u2019s<em> The Wretched of the Earth</em> discusses patients who suffered trauma during this conflict. The Organisation Arm\u00b4ee Secr\u00b4ete bombed Jean-Paul Sartre\u2019s house for supporting a side in this conflict. Francis Jeanson was tried for treason for supporting the FLN in, for ten points, what conflict that resulted in the independence of a North African country from France?", "answer": "<b> Algerian</b> War of Independence", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Damien Hirst\u2019s<em> For The Love of God</em> is a platinum cast of one of these objects covered in diamonds. One of these objects appears larger than life in a double portrait of two envoys to Henry VIII, Jean de Dinteville and Georges de Selve; that object is shown anamorphically, or distorted, on the floor in the front of Hans Holbein\u2019s painting of<em> The Ambassadors</em>. For ten points, name these bones, commonly shown with flowers in still life works by Georgia O\u2019Keeffe.", "answer": "<b> skull</b>s (prompt on<b> bone</b>s before mention)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "On one voyage, this explorer stumbled upon a lost member of the Narvaez expedition named Juan Ortiz, who became this man\u2019s translator. During this man\u2019s expedition, he gave the name<em> Esp\u00b4\u0131ritu Santo</em> to an area south of modern Tampa and released the ancestors of modern razorbacks into the wild. This explorer\u2019s most famous action is thought to have occurred in the town of Sunflower Landing in 1541 and allowed him to reach areas like Arkansas and Texas. For ten points, name this Spanish explorer who was the first to Mississippi River.", "answer": "Hernando de<b> Soto</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this cousin of\u201cChemical Ali\u201d and former dictator of Iraq.", "answer": "Saddam<b> Hussein</b> (prompt on Saddam alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A member of this faith wrote how Oxford and Cambridge were \u201csmothered in filth\u201d and was named Hester Biddle. The name of this faith came from a term used by Gervase Bennet involving the trial of one of its leaders. Early leaders of this faith included the Valiant Sixty. Minister Joseph Gurney caused a schism of this religious group, whose founder was inspired by an \u201cinner voice\u201d heard after a bout of drinking in 1643. George Fox founded, for ten points, what Christian sect, also known as the Society of Friends, who were said to \u201ctremble\u201d at the word of the Lord?", "answer": "<b> Quaker</b>s (accept the Religious Society of<b> Friends</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Terry Lenzner accused this man of funneling a bribe through Charles Rebozo to the President. Clifford Irving was sentenced to 17 months in prison for creating a fake autobiography of this man. The CIA asked this man to oversee the construction of the (+) </b> <b>GSF</b><em><b> Explorer</b></em><b>, meant to find a lost Soviet submarine. After this man died on a flight to Houston, part of his estate was claimed by the (*) </b> Church of Latter Day Saints in a forged\u201cMormon Will.\u201d This man lived in Las Vegas\u2019 Desert Inn for nearly a decade after a career as film director and airline owner. For ten points, name this reclusive American businessman who despised his H-4<em> Hercules</em> nickname of \u201cthe Spruce Goose.\u201d", "answer": "Howard Robard<b> Hughes</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The first victims of this event were 24 nonjuring priests being transported to the Abbey of Saint-Germain-des-Pr\u00b4es. During this event, the Princess de Lamballe\u2019s head was cut off</b> <b>and paraded on a pike. Some interpretations argue that the (+)</b> <b>Reign of Terror was a</b> <b>measured response to prevent a repeat of this event. This event was sparked by the Duke of (*) </b> Brunswick\u2019s invasion of France, and was carried out by mobs of sans-culottes. Georges Danton refused to stop, for ten points, what slaughter, during the French Revolution, of about half of Paris\u2019 prison population?", "answer": "<b> September Massacres</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man ended a revolt of the Mutayr and Ajman tribes after a victory at the Battle of Sabilla. This man negotiated with Captain William Shakespear and was finally recognized</b> <b>after signing the Treaty of Darin with the British. This man allowed Standard (+)</b> <b>Oil to</b> <b>utilize his country\u2019s petroleum, which had been discovered in Damman in 1938. This man\u2019s ascension began after defeating the rival Rashid family in the reconquest of (*)</b> Riyadh. Six of this man\u2019s 45 sons eventually ruled, including Faisal, Khalid, and the current king Salman. For ten points, name this first monarch and founder of Saudi Arabia.", "answer": "Ibn<b> Saud</b> (or<b> Abdulaziz</b>; accept Abdulaziz ibn Abdul Rahman ibn Faisal ibn Turki ibn Abdullah ibn Muhammad Al<b> Saud</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The medicine god of this myth system, Hatdastsisi, cures diseases through priests who flagellate the afflicted body parts. A woman in this myth system named Naste Estsan is said to eat children who misbehave and instructed women how to build the first (+) loom. Monsters in this myth system are turned into stone by lightning bolt-firing bows. The Din\u00b4e Bahane\u2019 is this myth system\u2019s creation story, and a (*)</b> trickster god in this myth system made the Milky Way by throwing bags of stars upwards and rolled human beings out of a ball of mud. For ten points, name this Native American myth system that includes Coyote.", "answer": "<b> Navajo</b> (accept<b> Dineh</b>; prompt on Native American)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A southwestern region of this modern-day country was home to the Garamantes tribe and has its capital at Sabha. A Greek colony near this nation\u2019s present-day city of (+) Shahat lent its name to another of this country\u2019s three historic regions. This country gave up its claim to the Aouzou Strip after the Toyota War. Fezzan and (*) </b> Cyrenaica are part of this country, whose internationally-recognized House of Deputies meet in Tobruk instead of its official capital. Ambassador Chris Stevens died in, for ten points, what North African nation whose cities include Benghazi and Tripoli?", "answer": "<b> Libya</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>After this man compared a leader to Yazid I in a speech at the Feyziyeh school, his subsequent arrest led to the protest of 15 Khordad. This man produced incendiary</b> <b>lectures on cassette tapes while living in exile in (+)</b> <b>Neauphle le Ch\u02c6ateau in Paris.</b> <b>This man\u2019s country uses a constitution inspired by his \u201cGuardianship of the Jurist\u201dphilosophies. This predecessor of (*) </b> Ali Khameini overthrew Mohammed Pahlavi in a revolution where his supporters besieged the American embassy in Tehran. For ten points, name this Grand Ayatollah who led the 1979 Iranian Revolution.", "answer": "(Grand) Ayatollah Ruhollah<b> Khomeini</b> (do not accept Khameini)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}